<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>(edited by Marian-Andrei Rizoiu) | Behavioral Data Science</title><link>https://www.behavioral-ds.science/authors/edited-by-marian-andrei-rizoiu/</link><atom:link href="https://www.behavioral-ds.science/authors/edited-by-marian-andrei-rizoiu/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>(edited by Marian-Andrei Rizoiu)</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>2023</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://www.behavioral-ds.science/img/logo.png</url><title>(edited by Marian-Andrei Rizoiu)</title><link>https://www.behavioral-ds.science/authors/edited-by-marian-andrei-rizoiu/</link></image><item><title>Detecting extreme ideologies in shifting landscapes</title><link>https://www.behavioral-ds.science/theme1_content/ideology_detection/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.behavioral-ds.science/theme1_content/ideology_detection/</guid><description>
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/csWMgU7R52Q" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen>
&lt;/iframe>
&lt;p>Also check out &lt;a href="../authors/rohit-ram/">Rohit&lt;/a>’s and &lt;a href="../authors/ma-rizoiu/">Andrei&lt;/a>’s article that just appeared in The Conversation: &lt;a href="https://theconversation.com/can-ideology-detecting-algorithms-catch-online-extremism-before-it-takes-hold-200629">Can ideology-detecting algorithms catch online extremism before it takes hold?&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.04097.pdf">our latest working paper&lt;/a>, we propose a completely automatic end-to-end ideology detection pipeline for the detection and psychosocial profiling of left-right political ideology, as well as far-right ideological users.
The pipeline fills a crucial gap by providing flexible methodology and tooling for understanding ideologies and building early warning systems for extreme ideology-motivated (and potentially violent) activity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Paper citation:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>Ram, R. and Rizoiu, M.A., 2022. You are what you browse: A robust framework for uncovering political ideology.
arXiv preprint arXiv:2208.04097.&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>(&lt;em>see full paper here: &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.04097.pdf">https://arxiv.org/pdf/2208.04097.pdf&lt;/a>&lt;/em>)&lt;/p>
&lt;div id="ideology-in-an-online-world" class="section level2">
&lt;h2>Ideology in an Online World&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Ideology determines how we make sense of much of the world, our opinions, and our political actions.
It is not a new concept; throughout history, it served as the context for unrest.
However, ideological spread and radicalization have entered a new paradigm in our ever-connected world. The internet is a significant source of information and spreads opinions quickly through social platforms.
In particular, the anonymity and lack of accountability often associated with online communication set up a supportive environment for spreading far-right ideologies and radicalizing individuals into extremist groups.
Far-right extremism is a form of ideology that advocates for ultranationalism, racism, and opposition to immigration and multiculturalism.
These ideologies strongly correlate with violence and terrorism and threaten individual and collective security.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Australian Security Intelligence Organisation (ASIO) raised concerns about Australians being radicalized very young and the rise of extremist movements in Australia through online technologies &lt;span class="citation">(&lt;a href="#ref-asio" role="doc-biblioref">&lt;span>“Director-General’s Annual Threat Assessment”&lt;/span> 2021&lt;/a>)&lt;/span>.
ASIO claimed that during the COVID period, 30-40% of their caseload was devoted to far-right extremism, up from 10-15% in 2016 &lt;span class="citation">(&lt;a href="#ref-guardian1" role="doc-biblioref">Karp 2020&lt;/a>)&lt;/span>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Unfortunately, Ideologically Motivated Violent Extremism (IMVE) continues to be an issue in Australia.
On December 12th, 2022, two Queensland police officers were killed while performing routine duties &lt;span class="citation">(&lt;a href="#ref-guardian2" role="doc-biblioref">Gillespie and McGowan 2022&lt;/a>)&lt;/span>.
Later investigations would uncover that the three people, who killed the officers, were active online in producing deep-state and religious conspiratorial content.
Their content has since been removed from mainstream social platforms but continues to be shared on conspiratorial websites.
Such extreme-leaning content often serves as a lead indicator of violent extremism (as was the case in this incident and the Christchurch Mosque Shootings three years prior). However, the tools to identify and understand the psychosocial characteristics of these extreme individuals and communities are lacking.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this work, we build an end-to-end ideology detection pipeline and psychosocial profiles of ideological groups.
We find that right-leaning individuals tend to use moral-vice language more than left-leaning and that far-right individuals’ grievance language (violence, hate, paranoia, etc.) significantly differs from the moderates.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div id="signals-of-ideology" class="section level2">
&lt;h2>Signals of Ideology&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In online social settings, researchers face numerous barriers that prevent using traditional methods.
Directly asking users for their ideologies has dubious success, infringes on platform T&amp;amp;Cs, and does not scale to online populations.
Inferring users’ ideologies from their activity also does not scale as the data requires is prohibitively expensive and tedious to compile.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Instead, to reduce expert labor to feasible levels, researchers infer ideologies from signals in user behavior – such as whether they use political hashtags, retweet politicians, or follow political parties.
We dub these signals &lt;em>ideological proxies&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Importantly, these &lt;em>ideological proxies&lt;/em> for online users can still require laborious labeling by context-specific experts.
For example, the hashtag &lt;em>#ScottyFromMarketing&lt;/em> requires an up-to-date expert in Australian politics to uncover that it expresses an anti-right-wing ideology.
For many researchers:
- access to contextual experts is difficult,
- labeling of signals is still laborious and expensive,
- and context switches require relabelling (exasperating the above problems).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Unfortunately, such context switches are commonplace, as the context changes with time, country, or social platform.
Figure &lt;a href="#fig:teaser">1&lt;/a> showcases the problem: most commonly used &lt;em>ideological proxies&lt;/em> can only be transferred in narrow circumstances (represented by the green dotted regions).
For example, following political parties is country-dependent, politicians come and go with time, and hashtags are platform-dependent.
As such, we desire an &lt;em>ideological proxy&lt;/em> that is robust to changes in context, requires no expert labeling and is true to the gold standard.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="figure">&lt;span style="display:block;" id="fig:teaser">&lt;/span>
&lt;img src="teaser_v2.svg" alt="Schema showing that not all ideological proxies can context-switch." width="700px" />
&lt;p class="caption">
Figure 1: Schema showing that not all ideological proxies can context-switch.
&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;!-- ![Not all ideological proxies can context-switch](teaser.png) -->
&lt;p>Furthermore, the &lt;em>ideological proxies&lt;/em> are often sparse among users; however, we would ideally like to detect influence amongst the entire population of users (as taking only active users could bias our inferences).
We further desire a method for inferring the ideology of (potentially inactive) users without direct &lt;em>ideological proxy&lt;/em> information.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div id="our-solution-you-are-what-you-browse" class="section level2">
&lt;h2>Our Solution: You are what you browse&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Our solution is a large-scale end-to-end ideology detection pipeline that can be used to profile entire populations of users.
The solution has two main components; the media proxy and the inference architecture.
The media proxy allows for labeling a subset of users, and the inference architecture allows for propagating these labels to the remaining users via socially-informed homophilic lenses.&lt;/p>
&lt;div id="the-media-proxy" class="section level3">
&lt;h3>The Media Proxy&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>For the first part of our work, we generate a proxy based on media-sharing behavior, which satisfies the desiderata.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We generate the media proxy via two media slant datasets (although many are widely available).
The first is an extensive survey of media consumption behaviors conducted by Reuters &lt;span class="citation">(&lt;a href="#ref-newman2019reuters" role="doc-biblioref">Newman et al. 2019&lt;/a>)&lt;/span> in several countries in 2020 and 2021.
Participants reported the media publications they consume and their own political ideology.
We estimate the slant of a media source for each country and year as the average ideology of the participants who consume it.
The second dataset is the Allsides Media Bias Dataset &lt;span class="citation">(&lt;a href="#ref-sides2018media" role="doc-biblioref">Sides 2018&lt;/a>)&lt;/span>, which contains an expert-curated set of media publications.
The Allsides dataset contains mostly American-based media; conversely, Reuters covers the major media outlets in each country.
Given that each country and period will have a different conception of ideologies, we calibrate Reuter’s media slants to approximate the Allsides (minimizing the mean-squared error). Figure &lt;a href="#fig:slants">2&lt;/a> shows the slants for each media website within the Reuters dataset.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="figure">&lt;span style="display:block;" id="fig:slants">&lt;/span>
&lt;img src="url_slants.svg" alt="Plot showing the slants for various media websites." width="700px" />
&lt;p class="caption">
Figure 2: Plot showing the slants for various media websites.
&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;!-- ![The slants for various media websites](./url_slants.png) -->
&lt;!-- We finally define the media slant of a media website, as its average over the country, year, and sources, and -->
&lt;p>Finally, we quantify a user’s ideology as the average ideology of their shared media.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The media proxy resolves the issue of context switching; since it is applicable across many contexts and can be used widely in a fully automated fashion.
This allows us to create an end-to-end ideology detection pipeline.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We further define methods to classify far-right users from their media-sharing behaviors, which we fully describe in the paper.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div id="the-inference-architecture" class="section level3">
&lt;h3>The Inference Architecture&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>In the second part of our work, we define an inference architecture that allows inferring the ideological labels of the remaining users – e.g., users who do not share any URLs.
Our inference architecture relies on the sociological principle of homophily, where we hypothesize that similar users will share a similar ideology.
We measure homophily through three distinct lenses;&lt;/p>
&lt;ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
&lt;li>&lt;em>Lexical&lt;/em>: Users with similar language will have similar ideology&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>Hashtag&lt;/em>: Users who participate in similar topics of discussion share a similar ideology&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>Resharing&lt;/em>: Users who consume similar content (signaled via resharing of other users) will share a similar ideology&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Through these lenses, we utilize an AutoML model, FLAML &lt;span class="citation">(&lt;a href="#ref-wang2021flaml" role="doc-biblioref">Wang et al. 2021&lt;/a>)&lt;/span> (with the LightGBM architecture), trained on users identified via an ideological proxy to propagate the labels to the remaining users and generate a complete ideological profile for a dataset.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div id="the-data" class="section level2">
&lt;h2>The Data&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We utilize several large-scale datasets from various platforms to showcase the relative ease of applying our end-to-end pipeline.
The datasets’ characteristics are described in Table &lt;a href="#tab:datasets">1&lt;/a>.
&lt;!-- For evaluation purposes, we use \#QandA based on the popular ABC panel show. -->&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;caption>&lt;span id="tab:datasets">Table 1: &lt;/span>The datasets used through-out the analysis, with the number of users, posts, and affliated country.&lt;/caption>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr class="header">
&lt;th align="left">Dataset&lt;/th>
&lt;th align="left">Users&lt;/th>
&lt;th align="left">Posts&lt;/th>
&lt;th align="left">Country&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr class="odd">
&lt;td align="left">#Qanda&lt;/td>
&lt;td align="left">103,074&lt;/td>
&lt;td align="left">768,808&lt;/td>
&lt;td align="left">AUS&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr class="even">
&lt;td align="left">#Ausvotes&lt;/td>
&lt;td align="left">273,874&lt;/td>
&lt;td align="left">5,033,982&lt;/td>
&lt;td align="left">AUS&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr class="odd">
&lt;td align="left">#SocialSense&lt;/td>
&lt;td align="left">49,442&lt;/td>
&lt;td align="left">358,292&lt;/td>
&lt;td align="left">AUS&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr class="even">
&lt;td align="left">Riot&lt;/td>
&lt;td align="left">574,281&lt;/td>
&lt;td align="left">1,067,794&lt;/td>
&lt;td align="left">US&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr class="odd">
&lt;td align="left">Parler&lt;/td>
&lt;td align="left">120,048&lt;/td>
&lt;td align="left">603,820&lt;/td>
&lt;td align="left">US&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;!-- ![The datasets we apply our pipeline on](datasets.png) -->
&lt;div id="psychosocial-profiles-of-the-ideological-groups" class="section level3">
&lt;h3>Psychosocial profiles of the Ideological Groups&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Large-scale profiling of entire online populations gives us significant insights into the characteristics of online populations.
We apply our inferred ideological labels of online users in two critical ways:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
&lt;li>We derive a method for distinguishing the left and the right in terms of their moral language.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We derive a method for distinguishing moderate and extreme ideologies in terms of their grievance language.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Distinguishing Left and Right&lt;/strong>:
We utilize the FrameAxis &lt;span class="citation">(&lt;a href="#ref-mokhberian2020moral" role="doc-biblioref">Mokhberian et al. 2020&lt;/a>)&lt;/span> methodology to metricize each user’s association with each of the five Moral Foundations &lt;span class="citation">(&lt;a href="#ref-graham2013moral" role="doc-biblioref">Graham et al. 2013&lt;/a>)&lt;/span> in terms of their vice and virtue axes.
Given the measures of the Moral Foundations in the user language, we can start to detect in what way the left and the right differ.
To do this, we find each ideological group’s mean vice and virtue scores and compare these to the neutral group.
Figure &lt;a href="#fig:mft">3&lt;/a> shows the outcome of this analysis on the SocialSense dataset.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="figure">&lt;span style="display:block;" id="fig:mft">&lt;/span>
&lt;img src="mft_diff_plot.svg" alt="Plot of the moral foundations of ideological groups in the SocialSense dataset, showing that the left prefer virtue and the right prefer vice language." width="700px" />
&lt;p class="caption">
Figure 3: Plot of the moral foundations of ideological groups in the SocialSense dataset, showing that the left prefer virtue and the right prefer vice language.
&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;!-- ![Plot showing that the left prefer virtue and the right prefer vice language](mft_diff_plot.png) -->
&lt;p>We see that the left prefers the language of virtue, while the right prefers the language of vice.
This trend is largely consistent across all datasets.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Distinguishing Moderates and Extremes&lt;/strong>: We similarly generate measures via the Grievance Dictionary &lt;span class="citation">(&lt;a href="#ref-van2021grievance" role="doc-biblioref">Van der Vegt et al. 2021&lt;/a>)&lt;/span>, a threat assessment tool designed to highlight potential threats through their language.
Similar to the previous plot, we investigate the distribution of grievance scores for the ideological groups.
However, here we measure the difference between distributions with the Signed KL-divergence (a measure of the difference in the location and shape of distributions).
Figure &lt;a href="#fig:grievance">4&lt;/a> shows the results for the Ausvotes dataset.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="figure">&lt;span style="display:block;" id="fig:grievance">&lt;/span>
&lt;img src="grievance_diff_plot.svg" alt="Plot of the grievance categories of ideological groups in the #Ausvotes dataset, showing that the far-right is significantly different." width="700px" />
&lt;p class="caption">
Figure 4: Plot of the grievance categories of ideological groups in the #Ausvotes dataset, showing that the far-right is significantly different.
&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;!-- ![Plot showing that the far-right use grievance language](grievance_diff_plot.png) -->
&lt;p>We observe that the far-right’s usage of grievance language is significantly different from the moderate ideological groups.
This adds evidence to the growing concern that members of the far-right may vent their frustration and participate in violent behavior.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div id="conclusion" class="section level2">
&lt;h2>Conclusion&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In this work, we build a fully automatic end-to-end ideology detection pipeline for left-right and far-right detection.
Importantly, with the pipeline, we can show the differences between the left and right, and moderates and extremes in terms of psychosocial language, across a range of diverse datasets.&lt;/p>
&lt;div id="references" class="section level3 unnumbered">
&lt;h3>References&lt;/h3>
&lt;div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
&lt;div id="ref-asio" class="csl-entry">
&lt;span>“Director-General’s Annual Threat Assessment.”&lt;/span> 2021. &lt;em>ASIO&lt;/em>. &lt;a href="https://www.asio.gov.au/resources/speeches-and-statements/director-generals-annual-threat-assessment-2021">https://www.asio.gov.au/resources/speeches-and-statements/director-generals-annual-threat-assessment-2021&lt;/a>.
&lt;/div>
&lt;div id="ref-guardian2" class="csl-entry">
Gillespie, Eden, and Michael McGowan. 2022. &lt;span>“Queensland Shooting: Gareth and Stacey Train Published YouTube Video After Killing Police Officers.”&lt;/span> &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/australia-news/2022/dec/16/queensland-shooting-gareth-and-stacey-train-youtube-video-published-after-killing-police" class="uri">https://www.theguardian.com/australia-news/2022/dec/16/queensland-shooting-gareth-and-stacey-train-youtube-video-published-after-killing-police&lt;/a>; The Guardian.
&lt;/div>
&lt;div id="ref-graham2013moral" class="csl-entry">
Graham, Jesse, Jonathan Haidt, Sena Koleva, Matt Motyl, Ravi Iyer, Sean P Wojcik, and Peter H Ditto. 2013. &lt;span>“Moral Foundations Theory: The Pragmatic Validity of Moral Pluralism.”&lt;/span> In &lt;em>Advances in Experimental Social Psychology&lt;/em>, 47:55–130. Elsevier.
&lt;/div>
&lt;div id="ref-guardian1" class="csl-entry">
Karp, Paul. 2020. &lt;span>“Asio Reveals up to 40% of Its Counter-Terrorism Cases Involve Far-Right Violent Extremism.”&lt;/span> &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/australia-news/2020/sep/22/asio-reveals-up-to-40-of-its-counter-terrorism-cases-involve-far-right-violent-extremism" class="uri">https://www.theguardian.com/australia-news/2020/sep/22/asio-reveals-up-to-40-of-its-counter-terrorism-cases-involve-far-right-violent-extremism&lt;/a>; The Guardian.
&lt;/div>
&lt;div id="ref-mokhberian2020moral" class="csl-entry">
Mokhberian, Negar, Andrés Abeliuk, Patrick Cummings, and Kristina Lerman. 2020. &lt;span>“Moral Framing and Ideological Bias of News.”&lt;/span> In &lt;em>International Conference on Social Informatics&lt;/em>, 206–19. Springer.
&lt;/div>
&lt;div id="ref-newman2019reuters" class="csl-entry">
Newman, Nic, Richard Fletcher, Antonis Kalogeropoulos, DAL Levy, and Rasmus Kleis Nielsen. 2019. &lt;span>“Reuters Institute Digital News Report 2018. Reuters Institute for the Study of Journalism.”&lt;/span> Oxford.
&lt;/div>
&lt;div id="ref-sides2018media" class="csl-entry">
Sides, All. 2018. &lt;span>“Media Bias Ratings.”&lt;/span> &lt;em>Allsides. Com&lt;/em>. &lt;a href="https://www.allsides.com/media-bias/ratings">https://www.allsides.com/media-bias/ratings&lt;/a>.
&lt;/div>
&lt;div id="ref-van2021grievance" class="csl-entry">
Van der Vegt, Isabelle, Maximilian Mozes, Bennett Kleinberg, and Paul Gill. 2021. &lt;span>“The Grievance Dictionary: Understanding Threatening Language Use.”&lt;/span> &lt;em>Behavior Research Methods&lt;/em> 53 (5): 2105–19.
&lt;/div>
&lt;div id="ref-wang2021flaml" class="csl-entry">
Wang, Chi, Qingyun Wu, Markus Weimer, and Erkang Zhu. 2021. &lt;span>“FLAML: A Fast and Lightweight Automl Library.”&lt;/span> &lt;em>Proceedings of Machine Learning and Systems&lt;/em> 3: 434–47.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Slipping to the Extreme: A Mixed-Method to Explain How Extreme Opinions Infiltrate Online Discussions</title><link>https://www.behavioral-ds.science/blogpost/icwsm2022/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.behavioral-ds.science/blogpost/icwsm2022/</guid><description>&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/HwFq3ywanp4" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen>&lt;/iframe>
&lt;p>In our &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2109.00302.pdf">recent paper&lt;/a> accepted at &lt;a href="https://www.icwsm.org/2022/index.html/">ICWSM 2022&lt;/a>, we propose a complete solution to accelerate the qualitative analysis of problematic online speech — with a specific focus on opinions emerging from online communities — by leveraging machine learning algorithms.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Paper citation:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>Quyu Kong, Emily Booth, Francesco Bailo, Amelia Johns, and Marian-Andrei
Rizoiu. Slipping to the Extreme: A Mixed-Method to Explain How Extreme
Opinions Infiltrate Online Discussions. In: Proceedings of the 16TH AAAI
International Conference on Web and Social Media, 2022.
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>(see full paper here: &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2109.00302.pdf">https://arxiv.org/pdf/2109.00302.pdf&lt;/a>)&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="problematic-speech-a-modern-plague">Problematic Speech: A Modern Plague&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Problematic speech is online interactions, speech, and artifacts that are inaccurate, misleading, inappropriately attributed, or altogether fabricated [1].
In 2020, the COVID-19 pandemic alerted the world to complex issues that arise from social media platforms circulating user-generated misinformation, hate speech, and conspiracy theories [2].
There are several primary types of quantitative methods for addressing problematic information, including large-scale monitoring of social media datasets [3], understanding platforms, users, and networks contributing to the &amp;ldquo;infodemic&amp;rdquo; [4], and predicting future pathways of information spreading [5].
These studies provide valuable insights into understanding how problematic information spreads and detecting which sources are reshared frequently and by which accounts.
However, these approaches often have less to say about why certain opinions and views gain traction with vulnerable groups and online communities.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Qualitative research methods are well placed to address this gap.
They provide rich, contextual insights into online communities&amp;rsquo; social beliefs, values, and practices, which shape how information is shared and how opinions are formed [6].
Nevertheless, a common criticism of qualitative research is that the in-depth knowledge comes at the expense of generating insights of limited representativeness and weak robustness of the findings.
Therefore, there is a gap between the depth of insight gained from ethnographic and qualitative approaches and the breadth of knowledge gained from computational methods from data science.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Our work fills this gap by proposing a mixed-method approach that combines qualitative insights, large-scale data collection, and human-in-the-loop machine learning approaches.
We apply our method to map in-depth and in-breadth the problematic information around four topics:
&lt;em>2019-20 Australian bushfire season&lt;/em>,
&lt;em>Climate change&lt;/em>,
&lt;em>COVID-19&lt;/em>, and
&lt;em>Vaccination&lt;/em>
on three social media platforms (Facebook, Twitter, and YouTube).&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="our-solution-mixing-digital-ethnography-with-advanced-machine-learning">Our Solution: Mixing Digital Ethnography with Advanced Machine Learning&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="fig1.png" alt="The pipeline of machine learning accelerated qualitative research where the human-in-the-loop machine learning algorithms are employed for dataset augmentation.">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We present a complete solution that bridges and facilitates qualitative and quantitative analysis to study problematic online speech.
The pipeline consists of three components which are detailed in this section.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="deep-qualitative-study">Deep qualitative study&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The first component is the qualitative study.
We build a platform based on an open-source tool, &lt;a href="https://wikiba.se/">&lt;em>Wikibase&lt;/em>&lt;/a>, where we conduct qualitative and quantitative analysis.
Through the quantitative study, we build an ontology of problematic online speech.
We label a large number of social media postings using their topics.
Simultaneously, we construct a vocabulary of 71 opinions that we also use to label postings.
Some example opinions include:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Climate change crisis isn't real&lt;/li>
&lt;li>United Nations is corrupt&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Climate change is a UN hoax&lt;/li>
&lt;li>United Nations wants to be the global ruling government&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Vaccines cause Autism&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The World Health Organisation is corrupt&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>These opinions contain mistrust in the government and supra-national structures (e.g., UN, WHO) and typical misinformation about vaccines.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="unlabeled-data-collection">Unlabeled data collection&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Qualitative approaches analyze emerging content and construct the vocabulary simultaneously when labeling the data.
However, they lack representativeness as they tend to be overly concentrated on narrow areas of the narrative landscape.
For this reason, the second step in our methodology involves collecting data at scale.
We collect large-scale raw data using the uncovered vocabulary from the deep qualitative study.
We construct keywords (shown in the table) for each topic to crawl social media data from three platforms.
We obtain a total of &lt;strong>13,321,813&lt;/strong> postings — &lt;strong>11,437,009&lt;/strong> Facebook postings, &lt;strong>1,793,927&lt;/strong> tweets and &lt;strong>90,877&lt;/strong> YouTube comments.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="table.png" alt="keywords">&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="dataset-augmentation">Dataset augmentation&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The next step is to annotate all the postings in our dataset automatically.
We employ machine learning algorithms to augment the data labeling process with a human-in-the-loop setting.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>By adopting the state-of-the-art text classification algorithm, RoBERTa [7,8], we first train the classifiers to identify problematic speech on postings annotated by the qualitative researchers.
Next, we deploy three strategies to select unlabeled data.
The active learning [9] strategy selects the data for which the classifiers are most uncertain.
The top-confidence strategy selects data that classifiers are most certain about.
The third strategy — the random strategy — randomly samples from unlabeled data.
The qualitative researchers then label the sampled data, introduce the newly labeled data in the ontology, and repeat the procedure iteratively until the predictive performance converges.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="humanintheloop-performance">Human-in-the-loop Performance&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We discuss here the convergence of prediction performance over labeling iterations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The following plot depicts the prediction performance on the test set macro-averaged over topics (accuracy in the left panel and F1 score on the right panel) over iterations.
The solid lines show the performance indicators, together with the cross-validation generalization error.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The cross-validation performance is stable across iterations.
This is expected as the classifiers learn from the same data on which the generalization is estimated — i.e., the classifiers are representative of the data they were trained on.
However, the difference between the test set performance and cross-validation performance is indicative of the representativity over the entire dataset.
The cross-validation accuracy is consistently lower than the test set accuracy because the test data is more imbalanced than labeled data.
The cross-validation F1 is more optimistic than the test set F1.
Finally, the difference between the two stabilizes for the later iterations, further suggesting the convergence.
&lt;img src="fig3.png" alt="Convergence of topic classifier performances over seven iterations.">&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="applying-the-qualitative-mapping">Applying the Qualitative Mapping&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We employ the obtained augmented labeled set to analyze the dynamics of problematic opinions at scale.
We machine-label the opinions in a large set of postings spanning over a long time, allowing us to apply the qualitative-defined coding schema to a significantly larger sample of postings.
This reduces the unavoidable selection bias of the deep qualitative study.
It also offers a critical tool for analyzing co-occurring opinions, which helps identify central opinions.
It is common for postings to express multiple opinions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We explore central opinions by building an opinion co-occurrence network in the online conversation of the topic &lt;strong>2019-20 Australian bushfire season&lt;/strong>.
In the network, nodes are the opinions captured during the bushfire conversation, while edges are present when both opinions are detected in the same postings.
The node degree of a given opinion node represents the number of opinions that co-occurred with it.
The edges are weighted by the number of postings in which their connected node opinions co-occurred.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The following plot presents each edge's daily proportions of weights among all edges between September 2019 and January 2020.
We show six edges (i.e., opinion pairs) to represent three types of temporal dynamics:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A continuous and relatively strong association between prevalent opinions — &amp;ldquo;Climate change crisis isn't real&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Climate change is a UN hoax,&amp;rdquo; which not notably is a conspiracy theory.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Associations with declining relative frequencies — &amp;ldquo;Greta Thunberg should not have a platform or influence as a climate&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Women and girls don't deserve a voice in the public sphere&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Rising associations such as &amp;ldquo;bushfires and climate change not related&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;bushfires were caused by random arsonists&amp;rdquo;; and also the conspiracy theory associations between &amp;ldquo;United Nations is corrupt&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;United Nations wants to be the global ruling government&amp;rdquo;.
&lt;img src="fig2.png" alt="Daily proportions of edge weights of six selected co-occurred opinions pairs.">&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>In the following plot, we map the co-occurrence network from posts published over 14 days in late September 2019, i.e., the period when the betweenness for conspiracy opinions is at peak.
This figure explains the ambivalent network role that conspiracy opinions can play: we first note a conspiracy opinion with relatively high degree and frequency — &amp;ldquo;Climate change is a UN hoax&amp;rdquo; —, while we also observe the presence of low degree but high betweenness conspiracy opinions at the periphery of the network — &amp;ldquo;Bushfires linked to secret elites&amp;rsquo; secret technology (chemtrails, HAARP, HSRN, geoengineering)&amp;quot;, &amp;ldquo;bushfires deliberately lit to promote a climate change agenda&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Australia should not be a member of the United Nations&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="featured.png" alt="A visualization of the co-occurrence network in late September 2020 — node sizes and colors indicate the degrees and betweenness values">&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="references">References&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>[1] Jack, C. 2017. Lexicon of lies: Terms for problematic information. Data &amp;amp; Society.&lt;br>
[2] Posetti, J.; and Bontcheva, K. 2020. Disinfodemic: deciphering COVID-19 disinformation. Policy brief 1.&lt;br>
[3] Ram, R.; Kong, Q.; and Rizoiu, M.-A. 2021. Birdspotter: A Tool for Analyzing and Labeling Twitter Users. In WSDM. ACM.&lt;br>
[4] Smith, N.; and Graham, T. 2019. Mapping the anti-vaccination movement on Facebook. Information, Communication &amp;amp; Society.&lt;br>
[5] Molina, M. D.; Sundar, S. S.; Le, T.; and Lee, D. 2019. “Fake news” is not simply false information: a concept explication and taxonomy of online content. American behavioral scientist&lt;br>
[6] Glaeser, E. L.; and Sunstein, C. R. 2009. Extremism and social learning. Journal of Legal Analysis.&lt;br>
[7] Vaswani, A.; Shazeer, N.; Parmar, N.; Uszkoreit, J.; Jones, L.; Gomez, A. N.; Kaiser, L.; and Polosukhin, I. 2017. Attention is all you need. In NeurIPS.&lt;br>
[8] Liu, Y.; Ott, M.; Goyal, N.; Du, J.; Joshi, M.; Chen, D.; Levy, O.; Lewis, M.; Zettlemoyer, L.; and Stoyanov, V. 2019. Roberta: A robustly optimized BERT pretraining approach. arXiv.&lt;br>
[9] Settles, B. 2012. Active learning. Synthesis lectures on artificial intelligence and machine learning.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Slipping to the Extreme: A Mixed-Method to Explain How Extreme Opinions Infiltrate Online Discussions</title><link>https://www.behavioral-ds.science/theme2_content/icwsm2022/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.behavioral-ds.science/theme2_content/icwsm2022/</guid><description>&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/HwFq3ywanp4" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen>&lt;/iframe>
&lt;p>In our &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2109.00302.pdf">recent paper&lt;/a> accepted at &lt;a href="https://www.icwsm.org/2022/index.html/">ICWSM 2022&lt;/a>, we propose a complete solution to accelerate the qualitative analysis of problematic online speech — with a specific focus on opinions emerging from online communities — by leveraging machine learning algorithms.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Paper citation:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>Quyu Kong, Emily Booth, Francesco Bailo, Amelia Johns, and Marian-Andrei
Rizoiu. Slipping to the Extreme: A Mixed-Method to Explain How Extreme
Opinions Infiltrate Online Discussions. In: Proceedings of the 16TH AAAI
International Conference on Web and Social Media, 2022.
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>(see full paper here: &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2109.00302.pdf">https://arxiv.org/pdf/2109.00302.pdf&lt;/a>)&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="problematic-speech-a-modern-plague">Problematic Speech: A Modern Plague&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Problematic speech is online interactions, speech, and artifacts that are inaccurate, misleading, inappropriately attributed, or altogether fabricated [1].
In 2020, the COVID-19 pandemic alerted the world to complex issues that arise from social media platforms circulating user-generated misinformation, hate speech, and conspiracy theories [2].
There are several primary types of quantitative methods for addressing problematic information, including large-scale monitoring of social media datasets [3], understanding platforms, users, and networks contributing to the &amp;ldquo;infodemic&amp;rdquo; [4], and predicting future pathways of information spreading [5].
These studies provide valuable insights into understanding how problematic information spreads and detecting which sources are reshared frequently and by which accounts.
However, these approaches often have less to say about why certain opinions and views gain traction with vulnerable groups and online communities.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Qualitative research methods are well placed to address this gap.
They provide rich, contextual insights into online communities&amp;rsquo; social beliefs, values, and practices, which shape how information is shared and how opinions are formed [6].
Nevertheless, a common criticism of qualitative research is that the in-depth knowledge comes at the expense of generating insights of limited representativeness and weak robustness of the findings.
Therefore, there is a gap between the depth of insight gained from ethnographic and qualitative approaches and the breadth of knowledge gained from computational methods from data science.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Our work fills this gap by proposing a mixed-method approach that combines qualitative insights, large-scale data collection, and human-in-the-loop machine learning approaches.
We apply our method to map in-depth and in-breadth the problematic information around four topics:
&lt;em>2019-20 Australian bushfire season&lt;/em>,
&lt;em>Climate change&lt;/em>,
&lt;em>COVID-19&lt;/em>, and
&lt;em>Vaccination&lt;/em>
on three social media platforms (Facebook, Twitter, and YouTube).&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="our-solution-mixing-digital-ethnography-with-advanced-machine-learning">Our Solution: Mixing Digital Ethnography with Advanced Machine Learning&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="fig1.png" alt="The pipeline of machine learning accelerated qualitative research where the human-in-the-loop machine learning algorithms are employed for dataset augmentation.">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We present a complete solution that bridges and facilitates qualitative and quantitative analysis to study problematic online speech.
The pipeline consists of three components which are detailed in this section.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="deep-qualitative-study">Deep qualitative study&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The first component is the qualitative study.
We build a platform based on an open-source tool, &lt;a href="https://wikiba.se/">&lt;em>Wikibase&lt;/em>&lt;/a>, where we conduct qualitative and quantitative analysis.
Through the quantitative study, we build an ontology of problematic online speech.
We label a large number of social media postings using their topics.
Simultaneously, we construct a vocabulary of 71 opinions that we also use to label postings.
Some example opinions include:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Climate change crisis isn't real&lt;/li>
&lt;li>United Nations is corrupt&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Climate change is a UN hoax&lt;/li>
&lt;li>United Nations wants to be the global ruling government&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Vaccines cause Autism&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The World Health Organisation is corrupt&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>These opinions contain mistrust in the government and supra-national structures (e.g., UN, WHO) and typical misinformation about vaccines.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="unlabeled-data-collection">Unlabeled data collection&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Qualitative approaches analyze emerging content and construct the vocabulary simultaneously when labeling the data.
However, they lack representativeness as they tend to be overly concentrated on narrow areas of the narrative landscape.
For this reason, the second step in our methodology involves collecting data at scale.
We collect large-scale raw data using the uncovered vocabulary from the deep qualitative study.
We construct keywords (shown in the table) for each topic to crawl social media data from three platforms.
We obtain a total of &lt;strong>13,321,813&lt;/strong> postings — &lt;strong>11,437,009&lt;/strong> Facebook postings, &lt;strong>1,793,927&lt;/strong> tweets and &lt;strong>90,877&lt;/strong> YouTube comments.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="table.png" alt="keywords">&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="dataset-augmentation">Dataset augmentation&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The next step is to annotate all the postings in our dataset automatically.
We employ machine learning algorithms to augment the data labeling process with a human-in-the-loop setting.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>By adopting the state-of-the-art text classification algorithm, RoBERTa [7,8], we first train the classifiers to identify problematic speech on postings annotated by the qualitative researchers.
Next, we deploy three strategies to select unlabeled data.
The active learning [9] strategy selects the data for which the classifiers are most uncertain.
The top-confidence strategy selects data that classifiers are most certain about.
The third strategy — the random strategy — randomly samples from unlabeled data.
The qualitative researchers then label the sampled data, introduce the newly labeled data in the ontology, and repeat the procedure iteratively until the predictive performance converges.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="humanintheloop-performance">Human-in-the-loop Performance&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We discuss here the convergence of prediction performance over labeling iterations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The following plot depicts the prediction performance on the test set macro-averaged over topics (accuracy in the left panel and F1 score on the right panel) over iterations.
The solid lines show the performance indicators, together with the cross-validation generalization error.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The cross-validation performance is stable across iterations.
This is expected as the classifiers learn from the same data on which the generalization is estimated — i.e., the classifiers are representative of the data they were trained on.
However, the difference between the test set performance and cross-validation performance is indicative of the representativity over the entire dataset.
The cross-validation accuracy is consistently lower than the test set accuracy because the test data is more imbalanced than labeled data.
The cross-validation F1 is more optimistic than the test set F1.
Finally, the difference between the two stabilizes for the later iterations, further suggesting the convergence.
&lt;img src="fig3.png" alt="Convergence of topic classifier performances over seven iterations.">&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="applying-the-qualitative-mapping">Applying the Qualitative Mapping&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We employ the obtained augmented labeled set to analyze the dynamics of problematic opinions at scale.
We machine-label the opinions in a large set of postings spanning over a long time, allowing us to apply the qualitative-defined coding schema to a significantly larger sample of postings.
This reduces the unavoidable selection bias of the deep qualitative study.
It also offers a critical tool for analyzing co-occurring opinions, which helps identify central opinions.
It is common for postings to express multiple opinions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We explore central opinions by building an opinion co-occurrence network in the online conversation of the topic &lt;strong>2019-20 Australian bushfire season&lt;/strong>.
In the network, nodes are the opinions captured during the bushfire conversation, while edges are present when both opinions are detected in the same postings.
The node degree of a given opinion node represents the number of opinions that co-occurred with it.
The edges are weighted by the number of postings in which their connected node opinions co-occurred.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The following plot presents each edge's daily proportions of weights among all edges between September 2019 and January 2020.
We show six edges (i.e., opinion pairs) to represent three types of temporal dynamics:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A continuous and relatively strong association between prevalent opinions — &amp;ldquo;Climate change crisis isn't real&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Climate change is a UN hoax,&amp;rdquo; which not notably is a conspiracy theory.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Associations with declining relative frequencies — &amp;ldquo;Greta Thunberg should not have a platform or influence as a climate&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Women and girls don't deserve a voice in the public sphere&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Rising associations such as &amp;ldquo;bushfires and climate change not related&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;bushfires were caused by random arsonists&amp;rdquo;; and also the conspiracy theory associations between &amp;ldquo;United Nations is corrupt&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;United Nations wants to be the global ruling government&amp;rdquo;.
&lt;img src="fig2.png" alt="Daily proportions of edge weights of six selected co-occurred opinions pairs.">&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>In the following plot, we map the co-occurrence network from posts published over 14 days in late September 2019, i.e., the period when the betweenness for conspiracy opinions is at peak.
This figure explains the ambivalent network role that conspiracy opinions can play: we first note a conspiracy opinion with relatively high degree and frequency — &amp;ldquo;Climate change is a UN hoax&amp;rdquo; —, while we also observe the presence of low degree but high betweenness conspiracy opinions at the periphery of the network — &amp;ldquo;Bushfires linked to secret elites&amp;rsquo; secret technology (chemtrails, HAARP, HSRN, geoengineering)&amp;quot;, &amp;ldquo;bushfires deliberately lit to promote a climate change agenda&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Australia should not be a member of the United Nations&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="featured.png" alt="A visualization of the co-occurrence network in late September 2020 — node sizes and colors indicate the degrees and betweenness values">&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="references">References&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>[1] Jack, C. 2017. Lexicon of lies: Terms for problematic information. Data &amp;amp; Society.&lt;br>
[2] Posetti, J.; and Bontcheva, K. 2020. Disinfodemic: deciphering COVID-19 disinformation. Policy brief 1.&lt;br>
[3] Ram, R.; Kong, Q.; and Rizoiu, M.-A. 2021. Birdspotter: A Tool for Analyzing and Labeling Twitter Users. In WSDM. ACM.&lt;br>
[4] Smith, N.; and Graham, T. 2019. Mapping the anti-vaccination movement on Facebook. Information, Communication &amp;amp; Society.&lt;br>
[5] Molina, M. D.; Sundar, S. S.; Le, T.; and Lee, D. 2019. “Fake news” is not simply false information: a concept explication and taxonomy of online content. American behavioral scientist&lt;br>
[6] Glaeser, E. L.; and Sunstein, C. R. 2009. Extremism and social learning. Journal of Legal Analysis.&lt;br>
[7] Vaswani, A.; Shazeer, N.; Parmar, N.; Uszkoreit, J.; Jones, L.; Gomez, A. N.; Kaiser, L.; and Polosukhin, I. 2017. Attention is all you need. In NeurIPS.&lt;br>
[8] Liu, Y.; Ott, M.; Goyal, N.; Du, J.; Joshi, M.; Chen, D.; Levy, O.; Lewis, M.; Zettlemoyer, L.; and Stoyanov, V. 2019. Roberta: A robustly optimized BERT pretraining approach. arXiv.&lt;br>
[9] Settles, B. 2012. Active learning. Synthesis lectures on artificial intelligence and machine learning.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>